<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St Maries in Cambridge, to the Universitie September the 6, 1668 the Sunday before the Sturbridge fair / by Edvvard Kemp ...</title>
            <author>Kemp, Edward, d. 1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19271</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11759999</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11759999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 539:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St Maries in Cambridge, to the Universitie September the 6, 1668 the Sunday before the Sturbridge fair / by Edvvard Kemp ...</title>
                  <author>Kemp, Edward, d. 1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Field ... and are to be sold by Edward Story ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge (England) :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, II, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48654:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARIES in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> To the UNIVERSITIE <hi>September</hi> the 6. 1668.</p>
            <p>The Sunday before STURBRIDGE Fair.</p>
            <p>By EDVVARD KEMP B.D. Fellow of <hi>Queens</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CAMBRIDGE, Printed by <hi>John Field,</hi> Printer to the Univerſitie. 1668. And are to be ſold by <hi>Edward Story</hi> Bookſeller in CAMBRIDGE.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48654:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48654:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:48654:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48654:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 CORINTH. Chap. 2. V. 17. The former part of the verſe.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>For we are not as many which corrupt,</hi> (or as the <hi>Geneva</hi> Tranſlation) <hi>deal deceitfully with the word of God.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text will give me occaſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeking it far or abroad to bring into view two very different profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; the Merchants, and our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Function. They are both here or rather the abuſes in them, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the eye, yet one ſtands but as the Metaphor to limn in more lively colours, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſturages of the other. To ſecular Trade, all wiſh well to the proſperity and managers of it, and whether we do ſo or no it is likely to thrive in the world, the Maſters and Wardens of it are ſo intent in the improvement, and have ſo many arts and wiles to drive it on; yet men complain (and they will ſo) of great decay; I ſuppoſe they mean they do not gather riches ſo faſt as they have a minde to do, and truly God, nor any the beſt times can ſatiate them in thoſe deſires.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48654:4"/>But I know not how our ſpiritual profeſſion hath got many enemies, whether envy to it, or ſlander upon it, or, which it is to be feared, our own infirmities (for we have this treaſure but in earthen veſſels) have made it much reproached, meanly thought of, ſtained, blaſted, wounded with evil tongues; nay ſome are come ſo far to malign it as to ſcruple our Miſſion, to cancel our Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to accuſe it of uſurpation, and making it ſelf a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and an incloſure which they would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; I wiſh I could ſay too that ſometimes even good mens mouths were not open'd againſt us, that we did not grieve and ſad even righteous and holy men; we had never more need of walking circumſpectly and warily, never more need of preaching with ſincerity, or in our Apoſtles phraſe to ſpeak the truth in Chriſt and lie not; for many errours have been ſown in the ear firſt, which have ſince taken root in the hearts of men. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul in my text intimates ſomething as if all were not right, no not in his days, but that there were mixtures and daſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in our ſpiritual wine, which he clears himſelf from.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are not as Many that corrupt, or deal dece it fully in the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where you have firſt, an accuſation. Secondly, a vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> accuſeth others, vindicates himſelf; he accuſeth, and ſo he may do in ſome trivial matter; No, it is no light one, it is of corrupting; but it may be out of ignorance, or errour of judgement; neither: it is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, wilfully, maliciouſly, for it is a cheat, corrupting and handling deceitfully: but perhaps then in ſome pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty merchandize; not ſo neither: a deceit in a ſtaple com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie in which all Chriſtian ſouls have a ſhare, for it is in the word of God. Againſt whom is this accuſation? not any ſingle perſon but many, a Corporation or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48654:4"/>
               <hi>many that corrupt, or handle the word of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully.</hi> And firſt of the accuſation, corrupting or dealing deceitfully: where we muſt ſomewhat take notice of the metaphor to which the Apoſtle alludes, To trade and deceits therein; ſo that without a digreſſion I might ſtep into ſhops and warehouſes, where though it is never ſo cunningly and cloſely carried, it is eaſier to detect fraud then reform it. I have as much an averſion from unfolding or ruſſling their goods as from plundering them; yet if Chriſtian advice could drive that devil of fraud out thence, and ſweep them from thoſe cobwebs and deſilements of deceit, perhaps trade might not have that curſe upon it as it hath of decay, which is now the complaint. I come not to their doors to reprovè them, but now ſeeing they are come ſo near ours, they muſt not take it amiſs, (for it is no arraigning of them nor of their commodities) though I put them in minde that if to God we muſt give an account of every idle word, then ſure of every lye that ſhall uſher in a deceit; of every geſture and hypocritical mine that melts the buyer to his great wrong and injury, to ſtake an unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able price for good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or any thing at all for corrupt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize.</p>
            <p>I know well that trade conduceth much to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of a people. I intend no invective againſt the induſtrious or ingenuous managers of it; they are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life, ſoul and Spirit of a nation, they ſerve not onely our neceſſities, but pleaſures, if not wantonneſs, pride and luxury too; yet we may not denie them their juſt nay honourable gains, ſuch no doubt have quick judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and wiſe heads to ſee, Chriſtian hearts to lament, nay warm wiſhes and deſires for the redreſs and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſuch ſordid abuſes and grievances, which have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48654:5"/>with much ſlineſs inſinuated into myſteries, to the great deflouring of the chaſtity of commerce and debauching it by diſſimulation, lies and arts of falſhood.</p>
            <p>I might further proſecute this Diſcourſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps very ſeaſonably at this time, though inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deviſes in trade are too cunning and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for me to take notice or give any character of, ſcarce any Craft amongſt them but hath hidden things of diſhoneſty; but I ſhall winde off, for indeed our holy Apoſtle doth but glance himſelf at it here, and ſo much he doth, (which is my warrant) he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that worldly commerce hath the ſtain of guile upon it, ſubject to be corrupted, and for us to deal deceitfully in; theſe being terms he borroweth from trade (to which deceit if it muſt be at all, I wiſh it were there confined) but here out of a holy zeal, he reproves it in a more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred merchandize where he found it was the moth that fretted it, even the word of God by our deceitfully hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, (And ſure if ever Divinitie learned their Arts it is much more ſince the foreman of the ſhop turned Preacher) ſince he claim'd to ſo much learning as to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Church Doctrine and Diſcipline, ſince cities by their wealth have ſo far governed the pulpit, as either to raiſe or abate Miniſters ſtipends and ſalaries, according as they ſhall pleaſe their fancies and ſooth their errours and ſins.</p>
            <p>It is not then the ſhop onely, but the pulpit too is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned of theſe deceits. And is not the Sanctuary free from them? have they builded their neſts in her Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets? Are not Gods Altars nor ſacred Oratories exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from theſe holy cheats? Chriſt overthrew the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and whipt the money Changers out of the Temple, but did he leave this worſer filth to defile it? I now
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48654:5"/>could make a further ſearch into ſecular Cheats or retire, and indeed I muſt not cover or caſt a veil upon our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall cozenages, though they muſt needs reflect upon ſome of our Function, and bring them upon the ſtage as very Artificial and cunning Traders, if not Corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Abuſers of holy Scripture; Scripture, the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of the Holy Ghoſt, truth delivered to us from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Prophets, holy Apoſtles, confirmed by miracles, water'd by the bloud of Martyrs, preſerved to us in all the Combuſtions, Changes and Perſecutions of the world inviolate: This is the word which the holy Fathers of the Church ſpent their time and oyl in to explain, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing vacancies even from their vigils, Canonical hours, Embers, Faſtings, and other Penances, to meditate on the ſacred merchandize which with exquiſite pains they unfolded, and aired (as it were) with pious Homilies and Comments, that no peſtilent breath of hereſies might pollute, nor errours ruffle or ſully it. This merchandize the word, they ſorted for divers Feſtivals, and with diſtinct portions of it celebrated them, fitted and adjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to anniverſary Commemorations of our Saviour, the Bleſſed Virgin, and other Saints and Martyrs. This is the word in which are treaſured up the moſt ſacred Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize that the world can or ever will ſhew: Nothing in it carnal, rich promiſes, oyl of gladneſs, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, ſeals of pardon, Gracious offers, ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, wholſome counſels, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Mary Magdalens,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and other penitents tears, the bloud of our Saviour, indeed what not? And if the Atheiſt, nor much more the hypocrite beleeves it not, (for the wantonneſs of wit, Drolleries and ſcoffs of the one, and Phariſaical quoting of it by the other, eſpecially when he is to ſerve his worldly intereſt by oſtentation of godlineſs, are ſome evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48654:6"/>to me they do not,) yet the word is ſtill the ſame, and retains yet its Glofy, majeſty, verdure and beauty, theſe drencht in pleaſures and ſenſuality are too mean and deſpicable to intice ſober Chriſtians minds from ſo ſolid foundations, and excellent ſtructures of piety, but that they will always be ready to pawn their very ſouls for the verity of it, and govern their lives and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by its holy precepts, laws and injunctions.</p>
            <p>Indeed the danger is ſomewhat more, and looks like a victorious miſchief, though the word it ſelf can never be foiled or worſted, being an incorruptible ſeed, which preſerves in it ſelf a pure and chaſte ſenſe, which neither Angel, Devil, or any creature can pervert; yet, when ſome men that are ſet apart and dedicated to holy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, who beſides the dignity of their Calling, may have ſome varniſh upon them of ſtrictneſs and zeal to ſet them off with the Vulgar (juſt as in trades they that would deceive to the utmoſt advantage, affect to have the repute at leaſt of conſcientious men above others in their dealing) ſhall with a daring confidence, nail an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation upon the holy Scripture; then whatſoever they hold forth is with many the very word of God it ſelf, the milk of the Word, The Bread of life, though never ſo unlike the candour, whiteneſs, and innocency of one or the other. And this gaudy ſhew of preciſeneſs, ſometimes with heat and paſſion againſt authorized De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies in religion, or ſlie touches wherewith we beſmear any eſtabliſhed Order in the worſhip of God, with the odious Title of Stinting or quenching the Spirit, or of Superſtition, (for which we have taken our meaſure before of the Vulgar, who are of the Combination:) This zeal cannot but win us the repute of godly, conſcientious, ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous tender men, and when we have once ſo builded our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48654:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>fame upon the premiſes, how faſt do we climb to ſuch an eſtimation, that our perſons are had in admiration, ſo that we may then de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> the whole trade of the pulpit, vend all ſorts of ware, good or bad; for people come to the Sanctuary reſolved to take them off our hands at any price, and never to examine the goodneſs, folidity, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptural worth or Textual Argumentation for them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not denie (which we have learned from my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries and crafts too) we put off good and bad merchan dize together) as one helps off the other in ſhops. The great and ſolemn Myſteries of Chriſts Incarnation, his Crucifixion, Death, Reſurrection, are expoſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to our view and our memories rub'd with them, (and yet perhaps not neither at their proper Feſtivals) to vend theſe they need no dark ſhops nor falſe lights; theſe are unqueſtionable, rich, indubitable verities which we all adore, and to which all our faiths ſtoop and bow; it may be too when they are in the frolick, they make, though not very quick but duller and cold exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to charity, and ſome few other Chriſtian Graces: men perhaps that have ſometimes ſmart touches againſt drunkenneſs, ſwearing, uncleanneſs, and we could wiſh they had had that good ſucceſs of their lungs, pains and menacing hell fire to them as to have ſtruck the guilty into bluſhes, horrour, repentance and amendment; but they have a concealing art againſt ſins of as deep and crimſon a dye, ſuch as they beleeve will not be cheap'ned or bought up by their Great maſters, or they reſerve them for other Marts, if they have any minde at all to vend them; they winde off and come not near Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, lying, forſwearing, cheating, hypocriſie, glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, covetouſneſs which is idolatry, ſchiſm and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; theſe are wares they rather let lie upon their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48654:7"/>hands, then anger the ſlie and cunning patrons of them; and beſides, they have their wreſted and forced Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, their rackt wines, either ſowr; or made liquours, ſtained, courſe, ill dyed, thrummed wares, ſtuffs (as it were) purpoſely dreſt and perfum'd for popular Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; for that is another art and skill in commerce to know when and to whom we vend one or the other: for all people are not eaſie alike to be beguiled: it is to the unskilful Buyer we conceal our beſt, and expoſe our worſt to ſale. To ſpeak plainer, It muſt be granted if any where, that wiſdom is requiſite in our calling, to know to whom we preach; for unleſs we watch oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to diſcover the ſeveral neceſſities, tempers, and wants of men, how to urge them, or forbear; to make our aſſaults, or to retire; they will ſcarce be ever our crown of rejoycing in the day of the Lord: ſo if we be otherwiſe bent to nouriſh ſin, luſts, or corruption in them (as both are much in our power by the Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion committed to us) we can never do that ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletely, artificially, and crafts-men like, as when we ſpie out their inclinations, and accordingly vend them incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and provoking drugs, dreſs our Ambuſhes, and oyl our words; theſe advancements and proficiencies ſome of us have made, even to the endangering of our own and other mens ſouls by borrowed Arts from wordly Trades, which ſupply me with one more by which they work de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and cozenages, that is, they have ordinarily falſe weights and meaſures which differ from the common and approved ſtandard.</p>
            <p>And it is as certain when ſome of us with weights and meaſures of our own, careleſs of the Churches ſtandard, which is the eſtabliſhed Doctrine in her Confeſſion of faith, and Articles of Religion; by which we ſhould mete
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48654:7"/>out the word to the people in our ſenſing and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, ſhall parcel out Scripture, and ſo vend it as it were by retail, and not in groſs; without a due regard to the whole ſcain, intireneſs, harmony and unity, or to what the rich and full ſenſe of one piece may ſupply to to the ſhort conciſeneſs and ſeeming vacuity of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how eaſily may we err and be deceived, and if any temptations lie in our way, (as very oft they do) eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of profit or popularity, deceive others, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, which is the height of the accuſation in the text, purpoſely and maliciouſly too. When we once lay aſide that ſtandard, the Churches expoſition, upon which God hath ſet ſo remarkably in all ages his arms, ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his motto and name; it is verily to be beleeved, at leaſt it is ſuſpicious, when we yeeld the balance to our own wit, underſtandings, fancies and inventions to hold it, that though it may go even to the eyes of men, yet there may be too, (as it often happens) more cunning then innocency in the hand that directs it: ſo needfull it is for us to hear, for the conduct and ſafety of ſouls to obey, and beſt too for the peace and unity of Chriſtians, is the Churches skill, ſincerity, uprightneſs and authority, that we can with no hands better truſt theſe weights and meaſures, the beam of the Sanctuary it ſelf, her ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and ſcale, who may and no doubt will preſerve its ſteadineſs, conſtancy and evenneſs, and is the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to beguile, deceive, or delude us.</p>
            <p>And this is a truth that experience hath taught us, that when people make light of the Churches doctrine, and are fond of new diſguiſings and interpretations of holy Scripture, the Prieſt ſhall eaſily comply with that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, nay by inſinuations and hintings to them much cheriſh it; for he is under no trivial temptations to do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48654:8"/>ſo: he cannot but foreſee the Mart he may open for all comers to reſort to; many paſſions are ſet on work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides pride which tickles him with the conceit of great abilities in himſelf to deceive; which confinements to an authorized ſenſe of the word reſtrains him from, and which, latitude and freedom cannot but gratifie him in, eſpecially having felt the pulſe of this age, diſtemper'd and bearing high with feavers, and new diſeaſes of refra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorineſs to Catholick Doctrine and wholſome words, and indeed with great inclinations and longings for fecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gloſſings upon the dictates of the holy Spirit, and divine and celeſtial verities: but now being maſter of the mint, which is in his eye, it cannot but be a gainfull office to him; for the Scripture will be a rich Bullion to coin what doctrines he ſhall pleaſe out of it, and then to imprint or ſtamp what gay and holy names he ſhall think good upon it. Indeed we ſhould be workmen that need not be aſhamed, yet though our pains is in the word, which is the fineſt Gold, we can mix much droſs of our own fancy with it, ſo that the ear-rings which we make out of it for the people, and veſſels which we frame for the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and Sanctuary ſervice are too too oft of a mean and baſer metall. We trade in the moſt holy of Grains, the ſacred Text; but it is ſo ill threſhed out and winnowed by ſome of us, that the wiſe buyer is loath to cheapen it, ſo ill it will ſerve for holy uſes, or bread of life.</p>
            <p>It is not long ſince (though I hope we are now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to a greater ſobriety, and primitive truth) that the Word, the Scripture, and its pure ſtreams, were fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomed, plummed, ſearched every bed, every corner of it, every grain and ſand of it to the leaſt ſcruple weighed, to ex authorize the Hierarchy, and to ſhuffle into the Church an Apocryphal Ordination.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48654:8"/>This Word that teacheth us exactly from whoſe hands we muſt receive our holy Orders, without which we ſhould not dare to miniſter in holy things; yet hath this been ſhamefully wreſted to decry all ſolemn Deſignment of perſons to holy offices, and to level the Function with the very loom. Theſe brave and gallant attempts have been made upon our Profeſſion, not by filings or waſhings of ſome ſcattered pieces or medals of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, but by melting down the whole Plate, the ſacred Text, every dram of it.</p>
            <p>This Word that allows no protection, no patents for committing any evil, no though good may come of it, yet have ſome culd examples out of it, and ſo have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion limned them out as handſome beautiful pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces not onely to look upon, but for imitation; as of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nees, Samſon, Ehud</hi> and <hi>Elias:</hi> and ſeeing theſe drawn with colours laid in oyl in the Scripture, that preſerves them yet freſh; ſome will not know, but that they may copy them out: but ſure we muſt not ſpeak wickedly for God, nor talk deceitfully for him; for ſhould now any be ſo furiouſly bold beyond any moderate zeal, to tread the ſtage as they did, and innocently might do, by ſome heroical Acts, which are not our meaſure: they muſt be ſure to have the ſame licence, commiſſion and anointings, the ſame ſpiritual dreſs and attire; even <hi>Elias</hi> his mantle too, which they can never for all their pretenſions and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminations wear or gird about them.</p>
            <p>This is the Word, ſo ſtrict in precepts, ſo ſevere in menaces againſt diſobedience to them whom God hath ſet over us: this holy Canon of Scripture, this ſacred Foreſt, in which from the talleſt Cedar to the loweſt ſhrub, is nothing but ſhade and protection for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Governours to preſerve their Crowns and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48654:9"/>from winds and ſtorms, the rude violence of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, nothing but ſap and oyl to anoint their perſons and to ſacre them: yet have ſome malicious wits feld timber from it, unbark'd, hew'd, hackt and expoſed it to ſale for fuel to kindle ſeditions, to put kingdoms into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtions, to frame new Common wealths, to erect Judgement-ſeats for arraignment, Bars for Princes to plead at; nay to build ſcaffolds and ſtages, and then to dye them with Royal bloud.</p>
            <p>This is the Word wherein as in a glaſs we may ſee our own deformities, and we that hold out this glaſs to the people, ſhould not make it ſo dim with our breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it; we ſhould ſo ſet it before them, that is ſo impartially expound the Word, that men may well ſee and view their many imperfections, frailties and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by which they have contracted paleneſs and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, much guilt and ſin; whereas ſome of us do ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly hold it, that they can ſpie in themſelves nothing but beauty, comelineſs, and excellent features, that they are the children of Grace: when had this glaſs been with leſs art and more innocency placed before them, not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a hollow vaulted and inclining wall, bending to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, factions, and adherencies; they might have ſeen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpots and blemiſhes in their lives which they daily ſport in, and converſe with, as new and freſh gueſts; yea and ſome wrinckles and furrows too, Cuſtomary, aged ſins which have long lodged and houſed in them; this artificial and dexterous repreſenting to men their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtate, indeed ſoothing and flattering them with the gay title of Saints and godly parties, whil'ſt they ſee their faces in a crackt glaſs by the divided word, or in the whole glaſs expoſed to them by ſome falſe light, in which they ſhew them unheard of marks and characters
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48654:9"/>of grace in them, yet ſeals to them of their election; which if the word were but truly, and without deceit applyed to them, would perhaps make them ſoon renounce and break in pieces ſuch counterfeit ſeals of adoption, and by all Chriſtian endeavour and a holy care even to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of thoſe graces, and call for more true and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to waſh them out. And this is ſo dangerous beſides a deceitfull handling of the word, i even to their ſouls, to whom they preſent this kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Saintſhip ſo unwarrantably as they do; that by this means, they keep them perpetually warm with conceits of I know not what purity, that they ſeldom but content themſelves with that, which they are aſſured from their Preachers gives them a title to eternal life and bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe Drainers of holy Writ, (for they quote it much) by opening ſuch wide ſluces to ſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, have dryed up the ſtreams, that is, made as it were uſeleſs the precepts that ſhould feed a holy life, to the impoveriſhing of the Chriſtian Common-wealth, and making us bankrupts of graces: a deceit and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenage ſo prejudicial to our holy Commerce, that we cannot but look upon them as great betrayers of the profit, treaſure and wealth of good ſouls, and will one day anſwer for bringing into this Mart ſuch wares as cannot but be forfeited, as no way vendible to ſober and well-minded Chriſtians. But it is leſs to be wondred at that men content themſelves with ſo few graces and good works to go to heaven with; even without purifying their lives and converſations, when by ſome of our Scripture-drivers they are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of eternal life and ſonſhip upon another account, which no vitiouſneſs or licentiouſneſs can reverſe, no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48654:10"/>good life can further, nor ill led life can cancel; and ſo without any further purſuit of true pietie and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs indeed, make a ſtand there, never ſeeing the errour they are ſoothed into; which is perhaps em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing filthy luſts, as ſpiritual pride and ſchiſm, for graces, and going away in triumph with theſe; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver looking back to repentance, humilitie, or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow (which we may well ſuppoſe was never taught them) for they were ingaged in thoſe ſins under the ſpecious Titles of Vertues and Godlineſs, are miſerably in the way to deſtruction; which theſe preachers have paved for them with wreſted and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Scripture.</p>
            <p>This Word is preciſe in all rules of holineſs and auſterities of life, mortification, ſelf denyall, taking up the Croſs: yet have ſome trimmers up of more generous Doctrine ſmoothed and kembed theſe Texts to the great ſatisfaction of the looſer, joviall and more ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Chriſtian; either by leſsning the weight of theſe Injunctions, or urging ſomething in favour of them, who have altogether diſpenſed with themſelves for ſuch ſeverities; if not by ſcoffs, taunts and cenſure of chaſtiſers of the body, as of moroſe, unſociable, ſowr tempers: But for taking up the Croſs, I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel not that that Text feels not much the hammer of our Commenting: we are unwilling to preach what people are averſe to hear, perhaps our ſelves not well reſolved to practiſe; and truly ſome have got ſo much, I think, by wiſe avoiding of ſuffering, that I ſhould wonder ever to ſee them in the bleſſed liſt of Confeſſours. Alas, they are too tender Chriſtians to endure ſcratches with thorns, though Chriſt himſelf our Head bleeded with them, and wore a Crown of them
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48654:10"/>in his Inauguration to his bitter paſſion. Indeed we cannot but conclude that ſuch texts in their hands are the greateſt ſufferers; which they torture, make confeſs, and extort from them what the holy Ghoſt never breathed upon; wiſe, politick Doctrines it may be, and ſo having ſomething of the Serpent, but few feathers of the Dove in them. <hi>He that would ſave his life ſhall loſe it,</hi> ſaith our Saviour: It is aſtoniſhment then to hear them boldly aver, that Martyrs were too eaſily won out of their lives and eſtates, too ſoon parted with and loſt all; to ſee them make ſallies from ſuch texts for ſelf preſervation, (which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed moſt in their eye, though Martyrdom may be in their tongue) to hear them put in their cautions and advices, leſt we ſhould unwiſely ſtrip our ſelves of the enjoyments of this life, and give our back to the plowers. Indeed leſt they themſelves ſhould not lay in proviſion to live in all times, in all chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and variations; leſt they ſhould be to ſeek how to clear Texts from difficulties, that may betray them ſome time or other to proverty or want; leſt they ſhould fail of Arguments to ſwallow once more all Oaths, or to demur upon alteration of religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nay without any niceneſs to ſtep into other mens livelyhoods, proprieties and eſtates.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe Rovers at Sea, and pirates in the trade of holy Scripture, exerciſe their violence and robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries upon the ſacred Text, ſinking with their force leſſer veſſels, wavering, weak, unſtable Chriſtians, which are a prey to them, and they eaſily boarded, and indeed ſeldom themſelves ſtrike ſail to primitive and unerring verity.</p>
            <p>I may ſoon tire you with the ſorting out of ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48654:11"/>doctrines, as are expoſed to ſale upon pretence that they are choice Balſams, Sovereign Reſtoratives, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled waters of the Spirit, coſtly ſpikenard, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, rich embroideries, fine wooll of the holy Lamb: ſuch names have they fixed to deſperate errours they have vended, varniſht, diſguiſed with the Word it ſelf, clapt holy Scripture upon them, to put them off with, and to drill the buyer. Such are Doctrines that wrong God, and injure him in his Attributes, his power, juſtice and mercy, ſuch as withdraw us from the love of God, our hearts and affections from him, ſuch as too much favour profanation, abhorrencies of perſons that are not of our adhevencies, perjuries, Sacriledge, ſchiſm, diſobedience, irreverence, ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods holy Service and Worſhip. Theſe can never come out of that Mint, out of that ſtore-houſe of holy Writ: onely ſuch as exhort us to doing of juſtice, ſhewing mercy, walking humbly, to ſtudy to be quiet, to do our own buſineſs, to work out our ſalvation with fear and trembling; to purge us from wordly luſts, that we may be veſſels unto honour, meet for the Maſters uſe, prepared unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good work. Theſe are Merchandizes, not ſhut up in tills or boxes; not upon high ſhelves that we need ſtretch our arms, wrench our ſinews, our inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to reach them; but they lie ſcattered, open, ſpread in every corner, in the loweſt desk of holy Writ.</p>
            <p>I ſhall take notice but of one thing more in this Text, Our Apoſtle doth not conceal, but confeſs the number of theſe Corrupters and Deceivers, <hi>Many that corrupt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly the world is much taken with num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48654:11"/>either ſeducers and deceivers, or the train that they draw after them. The Vulgar are much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with this gaudineſs, muſter and ſhew, and it is hard to take their minds off from this pageantry; if there be many of theſe deceivers, they take as it were fatisfaction to be deluded. The Apoſtle doth indeed take notice of the ſtrength of their Faction, and ſo may we too, without any blame in us; but perhaps, if it makes any great impreſſion in us, we may too much gratifie them in their vain glory: for they love to be admired, yes, and feared too upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for their Troops; none make more oftentation of the people, they boaſt every where of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which they produce, when either Reaſon or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments fail them: juſt as the Devil in the Goſpel did to Chriſt, My name is <hi>Legion; for we are many.</hi> Yet Chriſt for all that, and perhaps the rather caſt them out. I doubt not, though it be a kinde of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace to the government, thus to out-brave it with force; yet God will ſtill bear up both the Church and Crown, and ſtrengthen their hands to over-aw them that work now as Deceivers; but if their adherencies were ſo great as their friends would make us beleeve, they would quickly pull off their mask and diſguiſe, and ſcarce ſo tamely ask and ſue for that, which with more daring they could command.</p>
            <p>But in the mean while, it is the great joy of a Chriſtian to meditate and call to minde thoſe remarkable abatements and caſting down the coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and ſpirits of ſuch Deceivers (though never ſo numerous) by very late examples, when all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Force was theirs to make uſe of. And it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be a great refreſhing to all humble hearts,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48654:12"/>and ſuch as are ſenſible of our ſad fractions, that they can ſcarce finde any Faction that took content, and high complacency in multitudes; but God took ſome way or other in his good time to leſſen and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate their pride, either by the weak arm of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate deſerted, or by their own diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: theſe numbers, no good Chriſtian that hath a heart prepared to embrace what God ſhall allot them, (though it carries with it the face of never ſo dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and angry a perſecution) can tremble at or fear. Not that I contemn, or deſpiſe numbers; for I hope I ſhall always have in great veneration, the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Company of the Apoſtles, the goodly fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Prophets, the holy Army of Martyrs, and the Catholick Church throughout all the world. But I was always of that opinion, when by Gods permiſſion any ſtrong combination of men are knit together in detriment to the truth of the Eternal God, and caſting blots upon his Sacred Oracles, in unworthily betraying the true and pious ſenſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, to ſerve wicked purpoſes and practices; that neither their numbers, nor their cunning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances can keep them long from the ſhame that muſt purſue ſuch Sacrilegious Cheats: but as their numbers muſt needs melt at the breath of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, for ſo high an impietie; ſo their impure and ſtained cozenages and impoſtures are ſo eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected (though wilfulneſs may ſhut the eyes of the Vulgar) that their deſpicable troops, together with their ſcattered and routed falſities, will but the more at length dreſs out the triumph of pure and undefiled verity.</p>
            <p>To conclude all. Our Apoſtle is in our eye, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48654:12"/>he well maintains his innocency, and denies any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerity in his Doctrine; any deceit, cozenage or impoſturage in his preaching; which if true, he could not loſe his reputation in any thing ſooner: and I could wiſh ſome that are ready thus to hazard theirs upon the account of errours would conſider it. So unworthy a thing it ſeems to our Apoſtle, to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed a Broacher of Corrupt Doctrine, a vender of paint and fucuſſes, or indeed any thing that are mixtures and ſophiſticate, or that hath onely the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowings of truth, the fallacies of Arguments, and the pretty Romance victories of Errours to elude with; far from that humour which is now ſo common, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the Churches Doctrine as too mean a vaſſalage to ſubmit to; which truths perhaps may ſerve to ſo low ends as to ſerve God with fear, reverence, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and holineſs, to the ſubduing of luſts, hating of ſin, to lead men into the paths of righteouſneſs, and ſo to heaven; but not to the triumphs and glorious credit that vended errours may procure them in this world, (which is the brave deſigne they drive on) and truly they might do much to that end, but that ordinarily ſuch falſhoods light into mean Artiſts hands to dreſs, and into very dull ſouls to manage.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs ſay the time is come, that many conſent not to wholſome words, nor can endure ſound doctrine; but after their own luſts heap to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves teachers, having itching ears, and turn away from the truth; yet if we will indeed do right to our ſacred Order, win credit and honour to our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office, and to our Miniſtration in the Word; if we would have Chriſtians our hope, our joy, our crown of rejoycing in the preſence of our Lord at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48654:13"/>his coming, we muſt not be vain talkers and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſpeaking lies in hypocriſie, and teaching things that we ought not for filthy lucres ſake: we muſt ſhew incorruptneſs, gravity, ſincerity, ſound ſpeech that cannot be condemned; we muſt not deſire to pleaſe men, but God who tryeth our hearts. And we cannot have a more illuſtrious example then our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who walked not in craſtineſs, but by manifeſtation of the truth, commended himſelf to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans conſcience in the ſight of God; in all things approved himſelf as the Miniſter of God; by unfeigned love, by the word of truth, that he had corrupted no man, that Chriſtians were in his heart to live and die with them; and his words toward them were not yea and nay, or as my Text expreſſeth him and <hi>Timothy,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are not as many that corrupt the word of God, but of ſincority as of God, in the ſight of God, ſpeak we in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48654:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
